<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Doubtings dovvnfall first, prouing the communitie of the Saints assurance. Secondly, disprouing Bellarmines and his fellowes false allegations and friuolous exceptions against that truth. By Edvvard Dalton, preacher of the Word, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Dalton, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115432</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850651</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850651</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15872</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1513:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Doubtings dovvnfall first, prouing the communitie of the Saints assurance. Secondly, disprouing Bellarmines and his fellowes false allegations and friuolous exceptions against that truth. By Edvvard Dalton, preacher of the Word, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Dalton, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; cropped at foot.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, --  Saint, 1542-1621 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DOVBTINGS DOWNFALL, Firſt, PROVING THE COMMVNITIE of the Saints aſſurance. Secondly, DISPROVING BELLARMINES and his fellowes falſe allegations and friuolous exceptions againſt that Truth. BY EDVVARD DALTON, Preacher of the Word, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </bibl> Peſsimae matris ignorantiae peſsimaeitidem duae ſunt filiae, <hi>ſcil:</hi> falfitas &amp; dubietas.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Nazian. de modeſt. in diſput.</hi>
               </bibl> Vt in Creaturis primariae dona non aliquorum noſtri ſunt ſedomnium, vt vnius Creaturae communis eſt gratia: ita &amp; in fide, quae ſaluant, non eorum tantum ſunt qui magis poſſunt, ſed &amp; eorum qui volunt.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. l. de ouib.</hi>
               </bibl> Ille apud Deum plus habet loci, qui plus attulit, non ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti, ſed fidei.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 PET. 1.1.</hi>
               </bibl> To you which haue obtained like precious faith with vs, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IVDE verſ. 3.</hi>
               </bibl> Beloued, when I gaue all diligence to write vnto you of the common ſaluation, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 PET. 1.9.</hi>
               </bibl> Now the ſaluation of your ſoules is the end of your Faith.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable IOHN Earle of <hi>Annandale,</hi> Viſcount of <hi>Annand,</hi> Baron of <hi>Lough-Mauban,</hi> &amp;c. and one of the Gentlemen of his Maieſties Bed-Chamber.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F that ground bee truly iudged barren, which, receiuing ſeede, and partaking of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens dew and the Suns reflexion, affords no fruit: then much more that man into the ſurrowes of whoſe diſtreſſed eſtate a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious hand caſts the ſeede of compaſſion, and vpon whoſe diſconſolate heart a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable minde ſparkleth the rayes of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation may iuſtly be deemed ingratefull, if he bury in obliuion ſuch (eſpecially if vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerned) fauors. Euer ſince one beame of your Honors bounty miniſtred co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to my lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing ſpirits, I haue deſired, &amp; deſiring
<pb facs="tcp:15872:3"/>endeuoured, and endeuouring attempted to expreſſe my duty by preſuming to preſent vnto your Honour this little Plant, and to tranſplant it into your Honours Vineyard: little it is, yet beares it fruit already, and ſuch fruit, as (I hope) will yeeld conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting comfort and comfortable Content to each ſpiritual taſte for the preſent, &amp; leaue the relliſh of aſſured expectation for the time to come. It ſtriues to ouer-top the weeds of wants, wrongs, and woes which would weaken a Chriſtians patience, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the blaſts of diſcontents and diſtruſts which would ſupplant a belieuers hope and confidence, and to fruſtrate the ſtormes of doubting, and coniecture which would hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the growth of faith &amp; affurance. Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth your Honour to vouchſafe one hand, and to water it with a few drops of your fauourable approbation, it will thriue the better; and that, here, you may ſo flouriſh in Gods Courts, that branches be neuer wanting to your ſtocke, nor fruit to your branches, and that hereafter, root, ſtocke, branches, and fruit may flouriſh in the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall and eternal Paradiſe, he ſhall pray, who reſteth euer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours humbly deuoted EDVV. DALTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:3"/>
            <head>To the Gentlemen of the <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> eſpecially <hi>of the Temples.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE meaneſt of you may claime ſo much, and the greateſt of you is not diſparaged by that loweſt Title of Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Without you, we muſt confeſſe, not any in our Gouernment (which the Lord in his Mercy grant long to flouriſh) continueth or recouereth a certainty in his Eſtate Temporall, as you doe and will, I hope acknowledge, that you your ſelues attaine to, and finde comfort in, that certainty of your future well-fare by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, which as a Conduit pipe conuaies it to you from the Sacred Word,
<note place="margin">Eſ. 12.3.</note> that <hi>Well of Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The greater your care is for eſtabliſhing others or your ſelues in terreſtriall endowments, the greater coraſiue it is to the Conſcience, if it be not paralelld with an equall meaſure of ſtudie and endeuour to gather aſſurance of your owne Coeleſtiall inheritance: &amp; the more expence, wit, ſtrength and time is imployed about vſing the
<pb facs="tcp:15872:4"/>meanes to diſpoſſeſſe intruders vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others or our owne right, the deeper is the heart wounded, if ſome expence, wit, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; time be not ſet apart for the wreſting out of the hands of the truthes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries thoſe weapons whereby they goare the ſame &amp; in gulfe the Soule. What I haue done to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the point of the <hi>Communitie of the Saints aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and to remoue an vncertaine <hi>doubting of Gods loue in Ieſus Chriſt</hi> I referre (as my ſelfe alſo) to the cenſures and acceptations of you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſome of whom I haue ſometime liued, and whom I haue found alwaies both iudicious and generous: Praying, that you may all be ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and expert in the Law of man, that you <hi>Day and Night meditate vpon the Law of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> to your internall Peace here, and eternall Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for euer</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Your Worſh: to Command in</hi> Chriſt who is the end of the Law, EDVV. DALTON</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader deſirous of Reſolution.</head>
            <p>FOr thy ſake (Chriſtian Reader) haue I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled the euidence of thy preſent right to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe in a compendious maner: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther multitude of Leaues, nor greatneſſe of the Bole, nor number of the Branches, but the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Fruit is that which commends the Tree. Of thy confident <hi>hope,</hi> which is the <hi>Anchour</hi> of thy <hi>Soule,</hi> Heb. <hi>6.18, 19.</hi> and of the aſſurance of <hi>Faith</hi> which is thy <hi>Shield,</hi> Epheſ. <hi>9.16.</hi> the Romiſh Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, and Babiloniſh Fencers would depriue thee, and in their places intrude vpon thee <hi>doubting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture.</hi> In thy behalfe I haue entered the liſts, and for thy better ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; fuller perſuaſion through Gods aſſiſtance, haue wreſted out of their hands the chiefeſt weapons which they haue vſed to wound this Truth, and win the credit in this cauſe; ſo as I truſt thy conſcience (being good) will tell thee to thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that <hi>The</hi> Truth <hi>is great and hath preualled,</hi> and that, <hi>thou maiſt wrap thy ſelfe</hi> in the mantle of an humble <hi>aſſurance</hi> concerning the ſaluation of thy ſoule aſwell (though not ſo much) as any of the Saints which euer were or ſhall be. This I wiſh thee, and for this <hi>commending thee to God and to the word of his grace, which is able to build further, and to giue thee an inheritance among all them that are ſanctified,</hi> Act. <hi>20.32. I reſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine and the Churches deuoted ſeruant EDVV. DALTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:5"/>
            <head>To the ſeduced Reader.</head>
            <p>COnſideration of the vncertaintie of thy caſe (ſeduced Reader) hath wakened Compaſſion, compaſſion hath called vp Care, and care hath ſet on worke my thoughts, head and hands according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of my ſpirituall ſtrength to attempt thy help and to recouer that <hi>Hope</hi> which is vniuſtly (by thoſe who pretend to be thy Ghoſtly Fathers) held from thee. Thou wilt not build thine houſe vpon the ſands, and ſhall thy holy confidence be a Caſtle in the Ayre? This cauſe haue I brought to the Barre. Reade the pleadings on either ſide: wilfull ignorance is a double euill. Hauing read them cenſure indifferently: thou thy ſelfe wilt exclaime againſt a preiudicious &amp; partiall Iudge. Take heed of wounding thine owne Conſcience in ſlighting the Truth, for if thy Conſcience accuſe thee, God is greater, and as he can condemn thee, ſo he will cleare it. Thus praying that thou maiſt be <hi>turned</hi> to the true <hi>Shepheard and Biſhop of thy Soule,</hi> 1. Pet. 2.25. thy Sauiour, &amp; haue that <hi>hope which is ſure and ſtedfaſt,</hi> Heb. 3.6, <hi>and neuer makes aſhamed, Rom.</hi> 5.5. I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in any Chriſtian duty to be commanded</hi> EDVV, DALTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:5"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>POpiſh Doctors of all haue leaſt reaſon to interpret the Text of a Coniecturall perſwaſion,</hi> page 9.</item>
               <item>The Doctrine, is, <hi>To be aſſured of euery grace ſimply ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluation, is common to euery Saint, not Pauls peculiar.</hi> page 10.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>And it is firſt proued from the Text, not withſtanding Pauls</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Speciall Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> pa. 13.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gift of diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> page 15.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secondly, Context from the manner of the Apoſtles arguing</hi> page 26.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Marke whereat he aimeth,</hi> i. <hi>the Saints comfort</hi> page 28.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Grounds of thoſe comforts hee here laies downe</hi> p. 31.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thirdly, from the confeſſion of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, where</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>The Goſpell aſwell as the Law is particularly to be applyed.</hi> p. 32.</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:15872:6"/>
                           <item>2. <hi>To apply generall propoſitions particularly is the practiſe of</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>the Spirit.</hi> p. 34.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>the Aduerſaries the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues</hi> p. 36.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>The truth of Conuerſion may be knowne</hi> p. 38.</item>
                           <item>4. <hi>What heart it is which is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> p. 39.</item>
                           <item>5. <hi>Wherein</hi> Peter <hi>was deceiued, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was not</hi> p. 43.</item>
                           <item>6. <hi>It is abſurd to alledge Pauls rage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings against the Church, to proue a Saint may be deceiued</hi> p. 43.</item>
                           <item>7. <hi>According to the meaſure of faith is the meaſure of the Saints aſſurance</hi> p. 44.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>And it is ſecondly applied, therefore</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>They are reproued, who would haue all the Saints of God and members of Chriſt to doubt (and that out of duty) of their Saluation, of which to doubt Papiſts haue of all men leaſt cauſe, ſeeing (if we will beleeue themſelues) they onely are true beleeuers, and are able to keepe the Law</hi> p. 45.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>To hold doubting neceſſary is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, making Prayer fruitleſſe</hi> p. 46.</item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:15872:6"/>
                           <item>3. <hi>It is no preſumption to labour for aſſurance</hi> p. 48.</item>
                           <item>4. <hi>The meanes to obtaine aſſurance</hi> p. 50.</item>
                           <item>5. <hi>Signes of true aſſurance</hi> p. 50.</item>
                           <item>6. <hi>Outward conditions ſhould not puffe vp or exalt any Saint aboue his infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour brethren</hi> p. 51.</item>
                           <item>7. <hi>The meaneſt childe of God may in what eſtate ſoeuer he be, by reaſon of his intereſt in this aſſurance be comforted</hi> p. 52.</item>
                           <item>8. <hi>How to be comforted in ſinnes and ſufferings by this aſſurance</hi> p. 52.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15872:7"/>
            <head>DOVBTINGS DOVNFAL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROMANS 8. verſ. 38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come:</p>
                  <p n="39">
                     <hi>39.</hi> Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the predictions of our bleſſed Sauiour are infallible for their truth, and for their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments haue their periods: one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt ſeemes to be verified in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15872:8"/>our daies,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.26.</note> which is, <hi>That men ſhould be at their wits end, or their hearts ſhould faile them for feare, and for looking after thoſe things which are comming on the earth.</hi> Not that Chriſt would haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, but that men would be ſo, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with longing for certainties in things, rather of this then a better life: whereas if a man in the teſtimonie of a good Conſcience be once perſwaded that in Chriſt Gods preſent loue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption reflecteth on him, and future ioyes without intermiſſion doe expect him:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 146.2.</note> 
               <hi>Though the earth be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and though the Mountaines be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the midſt of the Sea:</hi> yet he (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his heart is wholly taken vp with the Lords Almightie power, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the Almighties mercifull protection, and fully perſwaded that the worſt croſſe,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.18.</note> euen the <hi>looſing of his head ſhall not produce the periſhing of an haire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>but all things ſhall turne to his good,</hi> though ſome through needleſſe feares <hi>make Shipwracke of Faith and a good Conſcience:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.19</note> other vpon earthly hopes embrace this preſent World) he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15872:8"/>I ſay remaineth as conſtantly faithfull in his outward profeſſion, as he is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily reſolued through an inward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion. But now the Apoſtle, partly ſeeing in the Romanes in his time, partly foreſeeing in all Saints in ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, that their holy perſuaſion ſhould be oppoſed and their heauenly profeſſion hindered vpon the ſound of that Alarum, which both preſent expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and future expectation cauſed to be made, entereth in this Chapter the liſts, and begins a combate with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of all ſorts, ſinne, and ſufferings (not ending many times till death hath put an end vnto them) nay death it ſelfe (of all afflictions the worſt which man can endure, and that only which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſiſt) from the 1. verſe to the 31. and leaſt any Saint ſhould ſhrinke from his holy faith, or any other be deterred from touching the very hemmes of that Religion which is ſo accompanied with afflictions and encountred with oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, he preſents the ſoule victoriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly triumphing from the 31. verſe to the end of the Chapter, againſt all doubt-cauſing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15872:9"/>ſtreights and heart-daunting ſtrength: becauſe it cannot poſſibly be deſtitute of any thing that is helpefull; <hi>for how ſhall not he that ſpared not his owne Sonne, but deliuered him vp for vs all, with him alſo freely giue vs all things,</hi> verſe 32. nor too much moleſted with any enemies that are hurtfull, whether ſeuered or vnited in their forces. Are they ſeuered? It inſults firſt ouer the malice of ſuch as are ſpirituall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne or Satan, and a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence through ſinne one or all, either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing verſe 33. <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? It is God that iuſtifieth; or condemning</hi> verſe 34. <hi>Who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen againe, who is euen at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for vs.</hi> Secondly, ouer the miſchiefe of ſuch as are corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, verſe 35, 36, 37. <hi>Who ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from the loue of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſword? as it is written, for thy ſake we are killed, all the day long we are counted as ſheepe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15872:9"/>for the ſlaughter; nay in all theſe things we are more then conquerours, through him that loued vs.</hi> Are they vnited? They ſhall preuaile no otherwiſe, ſpeed no better; for the Apoſtles conſcience told him that Gods loue to his Saints is inſeparable, and ſo inſeparable, that <hi>Neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come; nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able</hi> (endeuour what it will, attempt what it can) <hi>to ſeperate vs</hi> (either him or them) <hi>from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus our</hi> (his and their) <hi>Lord.</hi> A propoſition it is of comfort propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our Apoſtle in ſuch a manner we ſee, as manifeſts his aſſured and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible perſuaſion, not only of his owne, but of th Saints then in Rome, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of all Saints that either then were, or after ſhould be vpon the earth, their inſeparability from the loue of God in Chriſt. This perſuaſion was aſſured and infallible; for howſoeuer the word here vſed be ſometime taken for a probabilitie: yet other ſometimes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15872:10"/>for a certaine confidency and confident certainty as may be gathered by the Context and circumſtances of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where we finde it. Now the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text is the only touch-ſtone and rule to know the true interpretation of any word that is vſed diuerſly, and if this be not duly pondered, a man may, <hi>Toto errare Coelo,</hi> miſſe his marke, and looſe his aime, as by ſundry inſtances might be made apparent in words, which in diuers places of Scripture are taken in diuers ſenſes, if any ſhould, as none can, at leaſt not any will, ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of ſo weake a iudgement, ſo ſleight acquaintance with the Scripture, or ſo quarreling &amp; exceptious a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. Shall we then thinke that the Apoſtle aiming at the comfort of the Saints at Rome, and all other Saints, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all enemies whatſoeuer, inſulting before ouer great and mighty enemies, and euen modeſtly, yet truely and grauely boaſting, that he and others were <hi>Conquerours,</hi> yea <hi>more then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours,</hi> as if the victory had beene already gotten, would now finiſh his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15872:10"/>conſolations with vncertainties and coniectures? What couſtancy had this beene in an Apoſtle? What comfort to any of Gods people in their perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? ſhould not he, if here in the cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he be doubtfull, haue pulled downe all that heauenly fabricke and ſpirituall building of conſolation (which before by his confidence diſplayed by the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Lords <hi>turning all things to the good of thoſe that loue him</hi>) of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering</hi> and victory, euen in being <hi>kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> he had fairely raiſed and ſet vp vpon the pillers of ſound arguments? either his former boaſting was vaine, or hee now begun to bethinke himſelfe, in meeting on the ſudden with ſome bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aſſault, that he was miſtaken, or elſe in this argument, he is more confident then he was. But ſurely, ſeeing he was aſwell inſtructed in all truth, as ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened in all tryals from heauen, his tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing was holy, and his glorying was ſoundly grounded. And if he had beene ſo vnexpectedly aſſailed, with ſuch fury as to enforce him to recall himſelfe, and repent his former affiance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15872:11"/>without doubt it would haue clearely appeared in the face of his ſtile here, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as elſewhere, in that euery where (as the leaſt Conuerſant in his Epiſtles may perceiue) his ſpeciall care is, euer to preuent what may be obiected or miſconceiued: becauſe then we ſee no change in his countenance, nor alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his words, we cannot beleeue he either had any ſuch cauſe of feare or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to diſtruſt he was before in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: or if that will not be yeelded, yet without all contradiction, the brunt was quickly ouer, and the aſſault did not ſurpriſe him, or was ſo farre from the enfeebling of his faith, hindering of his hope, and daunting of his reſolued heart, that he is not only a man ſtill of the ſame minde he was before, but as <hi>Dauid</hi> vpon his good ſucceſſe againſt the <hi>Lyon and the Beare</hi> durſt aduenture to encounter with them,
<note place="margin">1 Sam 17.34, 37.</note> from whom all fled: So the Apoſtle hauing well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the greateſt violence of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, both might and malice, and to his comfort knowing now, that being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with the ſhield of the Lords pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15872:11"/>and ſufficiently armed with the loue of God vnto him in Chriſt, neither earthly nor helliſh power were able, to his eternall hurt, to prenaile againſt him, takes a neuer to be daunted cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to him, and enters the liſts a freſh as a champion ſtanding againſt all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and ready vpon the hazard of his ſoule to buckle with whomſoeuer or whatſoeuer ſhall call in queſtion either the certaintie of a Saints ſtanding or of <hi>the loue of God in Chriſt</hi> vnto him: for leaſt he ſhould omit any enemy or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, he challengeth euery <hi>creature,</hi> ſo farre is he in his confidence from a doubtfull coniecture.
<note place="margin">Popiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of all haue leaſt reaſon to interpret this Text of a conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion.</note> Of which they (Romes Rabbins) of all other haue the leaſt reaſon, and leſſe Religion, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this place, ſeeing it pleaſeth them ſometimes to tell vs that the Apoſtle had this perſuaſion by ſpeciall Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for ſuch things as the Lord reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in a ſpeciall manner are neuer falſe, but alwaies ſo certaine,
<note place="margin">Act. 1610. &amp; 18.9, 10. 11. &amp; 27.23, 24, 25. 34.</note> that a man may ſafely without any loſſe or preindice build vpon them; yea and hazard the ſaluation both of body and ſoule about
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15872:12"/>the truth and infallibilite of them. His perſuaſion then was aſſured, confident, &amp; certain, &amp; not concerning the inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilitie of the loue of God in Chriſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelf only, but towards the S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> at Rome alſo: for with himſelfe, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them, <hi>ſhall be able</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ſeparate,</hi> not me, but <hi>vs,</hi> equally inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſting them with himſelfe in the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Gods fauour. Now whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in this kinde the Saints then at Rome might challenge, al &amp; euery of the Saints to the Worlds end, may as iuſtly (euery man in his proportion and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) claime, elſe why was this reſerued in the Church, and propounded to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member of it, as of as neceſſary vſe as any other part or portion of ſacred Writ? In that then the perſuaſion of the Apoſtle is certaine and infallible, &amp; yet (as the Sun by the beames) is not bounded in the Spheare of that heart where it abideth but reflexeth indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently vpon the Saints at Rome, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſteth all the members of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">To be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of euery grace ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all gods Saints, not proper to any, no, not <hi>Pauls</hi> peculiar. <hi>Proued.</hi>
               </note> we may ſafely collect and conclude, that, <hi>To be aſſured of euery Grace ſimply ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15872:12"/>to ſaluation, is common to all Gods Saints, not proper to any, no, not</hi> Pauls <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar:</hi> for if euery Saint may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of one, then of euery, grace ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply neceſſary to ſaluation: but euery Saint may be aſſured of his owne inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parabilitie from the loue of God in Chriſt; and therefore it followeth, as neceſſarily as the Sunne is accompanied with light, that euery Saint may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of euery grace ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation. Now becauſe this truth is obſcured, and this Angelicall perſuaſion is held by ſome to be Satanical preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it will be no leſſe profitable then neceſſary to driue away all the miſts of error and miſdoubting by drawing the curtaine from before that light which 1. the Text. 2. the Context. 3. The confeſſion of the Aduerſaries giue vnto this concluſion.</p>
            <p>From the Text we may draw two arguments. 1.
<note place="margin">From the Text.</note> Of what grace ſoeuer ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as concerning himſelfe, is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly perſuaded, of the ſame grace, may euery Saint or regenerate Chriſtian, as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15872:13"/>concerning himſelfe be aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded alſo: But the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly perſuaded of his owne inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilitie from the loue of God in Chriſt, and conſequently of euery grace ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation: therefore, ſo may euery regenerate Chriſtian. 2. By what grace ſoeuer ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is aſſuredly perſuaded belongs to, or is in, others: they may be aſſuredly perſuaded, the ſame grace belongs to, and is in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: But the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly perſuaded, that, inſeparabilitie from the loue of God in Chriſt belongs to the Saints at Rome: therefore the Saints at Rome may be aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that inſeparability from the loue of God in Chriſt belongs to them: and if they, then of the ſame, may all other Saints whereſoeuer for themſelues be perſuaded alſo? Either of which two inferences, though they be as true as the Skie is cleare in the brighteſt day, yet a double exception, in ſeeming iuſt, will at the firſt glance, caſt a cloude vpon either of them, if not remoued.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15872:13"/>
            <p>The firſt is thus framed: It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, Becauſe the Apoſtle was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of his, therefore others may be perſuaded of their, inſeparabilitie.
<note place="margin">Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his 1. ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</note> Their reaſon is; He had that meanes which they want, namely, ſpeciall reuelation.</p>
            <p>But that cloude is diſperſed if one onely beame of the truth reflex vpon it, for the ground of this exception failes them being the 2. Cor. 12.4. for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place will yeeld them ſo much as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny colour of the like aduantage, where the Apoſtle comming to ſpeake of his viſions and reuelations affirmeth of himſelfe, that, <hi>He was rapt vp into the third heauen, and into Paradiſe,</hi> when and where they imagine he had this and other things, concerning himſelfe and other Saints reuealed to him, but how iuſtly they ſay it, let the place it ſelfe ſpeake, which affirmeth that he <hi>heard words not lawfull and not poſſible to be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered:</hi> but this his owne perſuaſion and aſſurance he here vttereth, which if it had beene vnpoſſible, he could not if vnlawfull he would not haue vttered; and therefore not then in ſpeciall maner
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15872:14"/>reuealed, if not then, I cannot beleeue at all, becauſe the word of God doth not reueale it.</p>
            <p>But be it ſuppoſed (we may ſuppoſe light to be darkeneſſe, truth to be error) that he had it reuealed; let them tell me the cauſe why he ſets downe, this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Reuelation, neither here nor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where as a ground of his aſſurance or as the foundation of his comforts, but only ſuch as are common with him to euery Chriſtian, and ſerue for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and perſuading any of the Saints of their inſeparabilitie from the loue of God in Chriſt: will they ſay it was his modeſty? why, that cannot be, becauſe Apoſtolique fidelity is, neuer ſeuered from, euer ioyned with, Apoſtolique modeſty, which appeares in this, that where he ſo ſpeakes of himſelfe, he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther implyeth or expreſſeth a reaſon of his ſo ſpeaking: But he that hath as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eyes as <hi>Argus,</hi> or is as deep ſighted as <hi>Linceus,</hi> can eſpy no ſuch reaſon here either expreſſed or to be collected. Surely then this muſt be the reaſon, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no better, no fitter can be giuen,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15872:14"/>that he conceales that ground of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red comfort which is proper, and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth thoſe that are common, leaſt hee ſhould caſt a ſcruple into the mindes of them (whom he would comfort) and make them not dare to apply that to themſelues, which did ſeeme to be his peculiar, and ſo depriue them of that conſolation, wherewith he did entend to fortifie them againſt all aſſaults and oppoſitions; and thus, this their excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion yeelds them loſſe for gaine, and confirmes what before I affirmed, namely, whereof the Apoſtle for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was perſuaded, euery Romane Saint &amp; conſequently euery regenerate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian for himſelf may be perſuaded alſo.</p>
            <p>The ſecond exception is thus produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Gift of diſcerning</hi>
               </note> The Apoſtle had the gift of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, of which he ſpeaketh 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. and affirmeth that to ſome it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; if to any, then to the Apoſtles; if to any of the Apoſtles, then to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.11.</note> for <hi>in nothing was he inferiour to the reſt of the Apoſtles:</hi> therefore he might know that of the Romanes, which they could not know of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15872:15"/>But this cloude with another of the truths rayes is diſſolued into ayre: for though we will yeeld vnto the Apoſtle, the preeminence for the meaſure by reaſon of that gift, yet wee affirme for the truth of the matter, that they, aſwell as hee, might be aſſuredly perſuaded that, <hi>inſeparabilitie from the loue of God in Christ</hi> did belong euen vnto them.</p>
            <p>For what is true of the Saints at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth in this regard, is true alſo of the Saints at Rome, and what may be ſaid of the one, may be likewiſe affirmed of the other, and of all other Saints. But the Apoſtle affirmeth,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.27.6.19.3.16.6.11.</note> that <hi>euery one of them is a member of Chriſt in his particular, that the Holy Ghoſt is, yea dwelleth, in them, that they were waſhed, ſanctified, and iuſtified,</hi> and conſequently had faith, that they <hi>were Chriſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.23.</note> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had him in them. Would he haue ſaid thus if it had not been ſo? or was it ſo? did he ſay it? and ſhall we not thinke he was aſſured of it? How will this ſtand with their exception,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15872:15"/>
               <hi>his gift of Diſcerning?</hi> How doth it agree with the grauity, and wiſdome, integritie, and ſincere dealing of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle?
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.14.</note> How elſe could he <hi>ſpeake all things to them in truth,</hi> as he affirmeth he did? It muſt needes then be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſeeing he ſaid it, he certainely knew they were ſo quallified: and yet notwithſtanding this his knowledge and perſuaſion concerning them, hee preſſeth vpon them, a fearching and diueing into their owne ſelues, their owne ſoules, for the finding and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſelfe-perceiuing of thoſe graces wherewith he knew they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued.</p>
            <p>Now if they could not haue found nor beene aſſured of them in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, I would know the reaſon, why for this hee doth ſo earneſtly preſſe them in diuers places, whether they <hi>knew their bodies were the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Christ?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.15.19.</note> 
               <hi>If the Spirit of God was dwelling in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.16. 2 Cor. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>whether they were in the faith and Chriſt Jeſus were in them?</hi> yea with ſuch a phraſe as doth more then imply, for it affirmes, nay,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15872:16"/>euen aſſures a neceſſitie; for he tels them if they knew not this they were <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they could not themſelues haue ſeen and certainly knowne theſe graces in them, theſe priuiledges to belong vnto them, then theſe preſſing Interrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had beene either very ſuperfluous (which to ſay caſts vpon the Spirit of wiſdome, the Author of them, an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of indiſcretion) or very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, vſed rather to enforce deſpaire, then infer comfort, or adde incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is blaſphemous, ſeeing it accuſeth the Lord as guilty of diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as though he colourably pretended ſure comfort, when he purpoſely enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aſſured diſtractions.</p>
            <p>My demand then admits no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer then this, that the reaſon of his earneſt vrging of them, was, to ſtirre them vp to a diligent examination of themſelues as he himſelfe declareth, that thereby they might haue experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>once of theſe graces in themſelues, which he teſtified, and teſtifying per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded them they had: otherwiſe hee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15872:16"/>would neuer haue gone about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade them, to whom he wiſhed ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the want of perſonall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe graces in them, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges belonging to them, was a ſigne of their <hi>reprobation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt we be thought altogether to roue in another field, and range among a ſtrange people (though indeed and truth the condition of all the Saints in regard of the ſubſtance and matter of all ſpeciall and ſpirituall graces be alike) let vs ſee if we can aime ſo right, and keepe home ſo well as to cleare this truth by any paſſage (beſides this Text) betweene the Apoſtle and theſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes concerning whom, he was here ſo well perſuaded. Surely there is one among others that addes ſtrength to this aſſertion, that notwithſtanding both ſpeciall reuelation, and the gift of diſcerning euery Regenerate Romane might be aſſured of that grace in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and of that priuiledge belonging to him, whereof the Apoſtle was aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly perſuaded in reſpect of him; and it is this. The Apoſtle giues God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15872:17"/>
               <hi>thankes that they</hi> (to wit which,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note> among the Romanes or elſewhere were effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.6. for till then, not any other are truly capable of any grace ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation) <hi>were,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">22.</note> ſome times, not now, <hi>the ſeruants of ſinne,</hi> that they <hi>were free from ſinne, and become the ſeruants of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">16.</note> and ſo <hi>free from death,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">23.</note> 
               <hi>and intereſted in eternall life,</hi> With what face could he haue come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord (though with praiſe in his mouth) who is the Iudge of all, who knowes the very hearts and reines, and whom <hi>hell and deſtruction are before,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15.11.</note> and therefore much <hi>more the hearts of the children of men,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> truly argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, if either he had doubted, or had not been vpon good grounds perſuaded of, aſwell their freedome from death, as the end of their holineſſe, eternall life? yet euen in that ſixt Chapter, he is euer and anon calling vpon the Romanes, the beſt among them, in that maner, and with ſuch a Phraſe, Tone and Accent, as not only imply a deſire he had to excite and ſtirre them vp to a cleare and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of theſe things which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15872:17"/>were in them and did belong vnto them, but alſo a ſharpe accuſation for their, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of them in themſelues, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their good eſtates in which he knew they were, and for which he pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth the ſacrifice of thankſgiuing to the Lord; for in the 3. v. of the 6. Chapter, his words are theſe, <hi>Know yee not that ſo many of vs</hi> (including them with <hi>himſelfe) as were baptized into Jeſus Chriſt, were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into his death?</hi> In the 16. v. theſe, <hi>Know ye not that to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you yeeld your ſelues ſcruants to obey, his ſeruants ye are to whom ye obey, whether of ſin vnto death, or of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto righteouſneſſe?</hi> The beſt we can make of his thus Catechizing them, and the leaſt we can gather from theſe cutting queſtions, is an earneſt calling vpon them to haue in themſelues experience of the benefits of Chriſts death and reſurrection, which through the whole Chapter are to <hi>die vnto ſin, and to liue vnto righteouſneſſe, and the end of all eternall life,</hi> which he knew did belong vnto them, ſo as of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer grace the Apoſtle is aſſured to be in, or to appertaine vnto, another; of the ſame may that other be aſſuredly perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded is in, or appertaines vnto, himſelfe. For whether they be Saints at Corinth or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15872:18"/>Rome or whereſoeuer concerning whom the Apoſtle is well perſuaded, hee grounds that his good perſuaſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, not vpon either ſpeciall Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or his gift of diſcerning, but vpon ſuch ſignes as they themſelues might ſee, and vpon ſuch tokens as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues might know and well perceiue in themſelues: for how knew hee that the Romanes were, before time, not then when he writ vnto them, the ſeruants of ſin, that is, had yeelded themſelues once wholly to the commanding power of ſin, but now had caſt off his yoke? He himſelf can beſt acquaint vs with the meanes whereby he attained to that knowledge concerning them: let vs aske him, our queſtion ſhall not be ſo ready as his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, for in the very next words, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth them,
<note place="margin">Ro. 6. verſ. 17.</note> to be, their <hi>obeying of the truth; yee haue,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>obeyed from the very heart that forme of doctrine which was deliuered vnto you,</hi> as if hee had ſaid, would you vnderſtand what moued mee to giue thankes to God for your preſent eſtate, and how I know you are free-men in reſpect of ſins bondage; I will tell you, thus it is, I ſaw and ſee and reioyce at it, that you with al the powers of your ſoules
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15872:18"/>haue yeelded obedience to that truth which hath beene taught you. How knew he that the fruit they ſhould reape was <hi>the fruit of holineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> and that <hi>the end</hi> they ſhould attaine to was <hi>eternall life?</hi> Then himſelfe none is better able to reueale vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what grounds he was moued to hope ſo well for their future happineſſe; and before wee demand he anſweres, there were certaine markes (Gods good to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens) vpon them which they might as well, if not better then he, perceiue in themſelues, and they were theſe, that they <hi>were made free from ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 22:</note> the yoke and burden whereof any Saint too much feeles, after hee by his corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſubiected to it, and to his hearts ioy well diſcernes, when by the Lords mercy in his Sauiours merits hee is eaſed of it, and then,
<note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> that they <hi>were become the ſeruants of God,</hi> that is, with all ſubmiſſiue reuerence, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerent diligence did reſigne themſelues ouer vnto God in minde, and ſoule, and ſpirit, and the whole man to doe his will, of which change, no childe of God can bee leſſe ignorant, then vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is a ſeruant of his owne remouing from a tedious painefull, and no way
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15872:19"/>contenting, to a ioyfull, eaſie, and euery way peace-bringing, ſeruice, ſeeing the ſeruing of ſin and Satan is bondage, and the ſeruice of the Lord is perfect freedom.</p>
            <p>As for the Corinthian Saints,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16.</note> He did in a mannet chide them, becauſe they tooke no better notice that they were <hi>the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,</hi> and that <hi>the ſpirit of God dwelt in them:</hi> and had he any reaſon for it? God and his Spirit are inuiſible, how then can mortall eies diſcouer their habitation. Though we doe not ſee the King, yet we can tell where the Court is, by the Writs that proceede from him, and the Retinue that belong vnto him. They could not but feele the impreſſion of the Spirit ſealing vpon their hearts, the eternall peace of their conſciences, the neuer expiring pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of Celeſtiall promiſes in Chriſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could they be ignorant of God and his Spirits preſence within them, ſeeing he could diſcerne that a <hi>ſpirituall ſanctitie</hi> &amp; <hi>godly graces</hi> did without adorne them.
<note place="margin" type="runSum">17.</note> Againe, It was an excellent priuiledge to be <hi>in the faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.5.</note> but an vnparalleld preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to haue <hi>Chriſt in them,</hi> and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which in the end bringeth happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without compare, to <hi>be free from the ſtate of reprobation.</hi> In all theſe regards he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15872:19"/>had affirm'd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their meaſure to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and withall theſe prerogatiues to be honoured with himſelfe:
<note place="margin">2 Cor 1.20, 22.</note> for (aſwell as he) they were by God <hi>eſtabliſhed in Chriſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, ſealed, and receiued the earneſt of the Spirit in their hearts.</hi> Neither was this a bare affirmation, but an aſſured perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning them;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.7.</note> for it was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſuch an <hi>hope</hi> of them for the time to come <hi>(hope is not of things ſeene)</hi> which was not fleeting but firme,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.24, 25.</note> it had not a ſandy but ſound foundation, &amp; what was that? could they alſo ſee it, to build their owne aſſured perſuaſion and ſtedfaſt hope vpon it? See it? clearey ſee it, palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly perceiue it, and ſenſibly feele it. Firſt,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.5, 7. &amp; 13.5.</note> their <hi>partaking</hi> of <hi>the ſufferings of Christ,</hi> &amp; then <hi>Chriſts powerfulneſſe in them.</hi> Such markes as are not only to be diſcerned, to be, where they be (for who can ſuffer and not know it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11. Luk. 24.4.</note> or haue a fire in his breaſt and not perceiue the heat of it?) bur common to all the Saints, to all the members of Chriſt, and to all that looke to enter into the Kingdome of heauen, for they that beleeue not in him will be ſo farre from ſuffering for him, that they will not ſo much as once take to heart either his or his Saints ſufferings, and if Chriſt ſhall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15872:20"/>not be mighty in them, they will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſufferings of any kind for him. Thus from the Text the double collection (that euery regenerate Chriſtian may be aſſured of whatſoeuer grace for himſelfe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Apoſtle is perſuaded for himſelf, or in the behalfe of any other, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either ſpeciall Reuelation, or his gift of diſcerning) remaineth vndenyable.</p>
            <p>No leſſe,
<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to be common from.</note> but rather more tranſparent light will the Context giue to this truth, That to be aſſured of inſeparabilitie from the loue of God in Chriſt, and ſo of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation is not proper to the Apoſtle nor any Saint, but common to euery one of the S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by, 1. the Maner. 2. the Marke. 3. the ground of <hi>Pauls</hi> arguing in this Chap.</p>
            <p>For the 1.
<note place="margin">1. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Apoſtles arguing.</note> the Maner. It is neceſſarily granted, that <hi>Freedome from condemnation.</hi> To be the <hi>childe of God, Saluation, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the holy Ghoſt, and of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To haue <hi>all things worke together</hi> for the beſt, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictory in Tribulations,</hi> and the like. <hi>Inſeparabilitie from the loue of Chriſt and God in Chriſt,</hi> are things ſimply neceſſary. Now the Apoſtle vſing theſe as argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of comfort, he doth not appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate them, nor any one of them to himſelfe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15872:20"/>but applyeth them, to himſelfe indeed, for he is included, yet, ſo as the reſt of the faithfull alſo may include themſelues. This he would not, nay could not, haue done without deluding of them, if they might only haue ſeene the Combe, and might not haue taſted of the Hony, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude them was as farre from his intention as it ſhould be fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our imagination, ſeeing he ſought to approue himſelf in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of all, which he could not haue done though he had vſed neuer ſo great endeuor, nor truly haue endeuoured, if he in theſe priuileges me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, might only haue cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged a property &amp; the reſt of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full could at all haue claymed no intereſt.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith not; <hi>There is no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to mee</hi> but <hi>to them,</hi> be what they will be, ſo they <hi>be in Crriſt Jeſus, &amp; walk not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh but after the ſpirit.</hi> He ſaith not that he only is the child of God, but <hi>as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as are led by the ſpirit of God, they are the ſons of God.</hi> He ſaith not he is, but <hi>we are ſaued by hope.</hi> He ſaith not all <hi>things worke together for good</hi> to me, but <hi>to them that loue God, to them who are called according to his purpoſe.</hi> He ſaith not, <hi>either the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or Christ makes interceſſion</hi> for mee, but for <hi>vs.</hi> Hee ſaith not, <hi>in all theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15872:21"/>things</hi> I am more then a Conquerour, but <hi>we are more then Conquerours through him that loued</hi> not me but <hi>vs,</hi> He ſaith not <hi>who ſhall ſeparate</hi> me but <hi>vs from the loue of Chriſt?</hi> nor, <hi>I am perſuaded, that neither death nor life &amp;c. ſhall be able to ſeperate me but vs from the loue God &amp;c.</hi> as freely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſſing and fully inueſting the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Saints then in Rome and all others, who had or ſhall haue the conditions which are added, in thoſe priuiledges and graces, as he was fully and certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded they belonged to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond,
<note place="margin">2. That at which the Apoſtle ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <hi>i.</hi> the comforts of all the Sts.</note> The marke or end where at the Apoſtle in this place aimeth, what is it? It is the comfort &amp; conſolation not of himſelfe alone, but of euery regenerate Romane, and conſequently of euery truly beleeuing Chriſtian which was then, is now, or hereafter ſhall be in Chriſt Ieſus, againſt all and ſingular enemies and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites whatſoeuer which might any way leſſen, or by any means cauſe them to leaue their confidence in Gods loue through Chriſt, elſe he might better haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed theſe comforts in the cloſet of his owne breaſt then reuealed them. And further to ſay theſe comforts here recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded either all or ſome of them doe belong
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15872:21"/>vnto him alone, is erronious: for to ſay, they all are his in peculiar, is to gaineſay his purpoſe here, becauſe the bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits purpoſe, and his owne ſpeach elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, where he who was no changeling in his aſſertions affirmeth that <hi>Whatſoeuer things were written aforetime were written for our learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>that wee through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and comfort of the Scriptures might haue hope:</hi> which things <hi>(patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort)</hi> by them <hi>(the Scriptures)</hi> are the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits aime, their <hi>(the Scriptures)</hi> end not only in the Apoſtles time, but to the worlds end. Now how can we be armed with patience, ſuſtained with comfort, &amp; tranſported to the hauen of happineſſe, with hope by this Scripture an only place of comfort, yea euen of all places fulleſt of the ſpirituall Balme of Gilead if it wholly belongs to <hi>Paul?</hi> If it it wholy belongs to <hi>Paul</hi> how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it otherwiſe be thought, but that, he <hi>ſought</hi> only <hi>himſelfe</hi> &amp; his own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, neither the Saints then, nor vs now?</p>
            <p>To affirme that ſome of them belonged to him, preſuppoſeth this particular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort laid downe in this Text, the inſeparability from the loue of God in Chriſt, which is the greateſt, and comprehends the reſt, &amp; therefore if any, then this; if this, how is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15872:22"/>not the Apoſtle (as was euery one of the three friends of <hi>Iob</hi>) a miſerable comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a diſtreſſed conſcience?
<note place="margin">Iob. 13.4. &amp; 16.2. &amp; 2.12, 13.</note> for as <hi>they caſt duſt vpon their heads, and ſate by him ſeauen daies and ſeauen nights together ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull,</hi> yet at laſt failed in applying com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: So hee hauing animated a fainting ſoule, refreſhed a wearied ſpirit, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled a wounded heart with ſundry ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Cordials againſt the rigour of the law, the frailtie of the fleſh, the greatneſſe and grieuouſneſſe of afflictions a long time, ſhould leaue that ſoule ſo languiſhing, that ſpirit ſo weary, that heart ſo wounded in danger of the laſt enemie, and in doubt of none of the leaſt mercies: for not one but euery faithfull ſoule perceiuing it muſt, though it haue foiled many aduerſaries, faile in the end wholly, and faint vnder the burden of one or other oppoſition, &amp; not obtain the end of its hope and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>the loue of God in Chriſt</hi> is plunged deep in the gulfe of deſperation; and ſo would <hi>Paul</hi> become the ſauour of life to none, the ſauour of death to all euen thoſe which are coheires with him in Chriſt, which muſt not ſo much as once into our thoughts bee admitted or in our minds conceited, much leſſe with our mouthes be vttered, ſeeing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15872:22"/>the holy Ghoſt affirms,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.15, 16.</note> that he was <hi>the</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall <hi>ſauour of life</hi> to the Fathers cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and to the Sonnes redeemed.</p>
            <p>For the 3.
<note place="margin">3. The ground of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts.</note> thing conſidered in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, the Ground of <hi>Pauls</hi> arguing &amp; of his comforts here laid down, are of two ſorts, the one <hi>working, Gods loue &amp; mercy, Chriſts merits &amp; efficacie;</hi> the other witneſſing, <hi>Gods ſpirit &amp; our ſpirit, or a renued conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Now all &amp; euery of theſe cannot but be affirmed, muſt neceſſarily be confeſſed, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all, not only proper to any of the faithful: for to deny theſe, one or any of them to one or any belieuer, is to deny him, to be elected which proceedes from <hi>Gods loue,</hi> to bee redeemed which is of <hi>Chriſts merit,</hi> to be ſanctified which is the <hi>work of the ſpirit,</hi> ſeeing therfore the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, of this his inſeparability fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods loue in Chriſt, &amp; of the other priuiledges is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I conclude that, To be perſuaded of, &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in, theſe, is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to euery truly regenerated Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Thus the Text and Context cleare our concluſion,
<note place="margin">Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> but that wherein we may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly triumph, and which is not of the leaſt force both to confound the perſons &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute their opinions, is, their owne Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For (ſay they) if there were either a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15872:23"/>word,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Iuſtof. c.</hi> 8.</note> ſaying to euery particular perſon, as our Sauiour to the ſicke of the palſie, <hi>Sonne thy ſins be forgiuen thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 9.2.</note> or we could certainely know the truth of our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, we might freely conclude &amp; conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding aſſure our ſelues, that we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſeparated from the loue of God in Chriſt, but (which is all one) be ſaued, that our ſins are pardoned, we are iuſtified and ſhall be glorified: But there is (ſay the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of this truth) no ſuch particular promiſe reuealed now, by name or in that maner to any particular Saint in or by the word: nor any ſuch aſſurance of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion can be apprehended: therefore we cannot be aſſured either our ſinnes are pardoned, or wee neuer ſhall be ſeuered from the loue of God in Chriſt, or at laſt ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            <p>The firſt is friuolous,
<note place="margin">Generall propoſitions particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to be applyed.</note> the ſecond falſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt is friuolous: for let them tell me, is not the Goſpel the ſame for comfort that the Law is for terror, to the ſoule? muſt the ſoule apprehend, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding apply in particuler to it ſelfe, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall precepts prohibitions and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Law, and may it not in like maner apprehend and apply,
<note place="margin">The Goſpel aſwell as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in particuler to it ſelfe the generall promiſes and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15872:23"/>of the Goſpell? how is the <hi>Lords mercy ouer all his workes?</hi> is his hand of fauour ſhorter then his hand of fury?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.7, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Hath the Lord forgotten to be mercifull, and doth he thus ſhut vp his louing kindneſſe in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</hi> Is his Mercy thus ſmothered by Iuſtice? and hath his Iuſtice got the ſtart ſo far of Mercy? Muſt I ſwallow the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; may I not taſte the Antidote? muſt I lay to my ſore the Corafiue only, &amp; may I in no caſe apply the Plaiſter? Shall an heire into whoſe hands the entaile of his Anceſtors inheritance commeth, reading the euidence (knowing there is none other to debar him of it, though he cannot finde his owne name in particuler, &amp; his dead Anceſtors being ſo tong-tied that they cannot ſpeake) not conclude I am of the ſame linage, and therefore this inheritance doth belong vnto me? and may not euery Saint and member of Chriſt in particuler, knowing himſelf to be a ſpiritual heire of <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 3.25, 26.</note> reading the Letters Patents of the King of Heauen, ſeeing the Kings Seale, &amp; hauing all committed to his own vſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the benefit of this blelongs vnto him, ſeeing his father could not cancell it, his Soueraigne would not, neither can any pretend title to his preiudice? for though
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15872:24"/>there be many, yet his intereſt is as good, though perhaps not ſo great, why ſhould not he then apprehend it as his own right in particular? Be the words neuer ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall he may ſafely inferre the particuler, for this is the practice of the holy Ghoſt, nay; and the aduerſaries themſelues make the like concluſion.</p>
            <p>It is the practiſe of the bleſſed ſpirit ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to apply a particular to a general vſe,
<note place="margin">To apply particularly generall propofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is the practiſe of the Spirit.</note> ſometime caſting that couer (which will ſerue a multitude) vpon a few; and again healing the wounded heart of one with thoſe plaiſters which had bin applyed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many. The Apoſtle applieth &amp; challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to himſelfe &amp; others the ſame which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> alledgeth of himſelfe, Seeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith he, that we haue the ſame ſpirit of faith, according as it is written, <hi>I beleeued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 116.10. 2 Cor. 4.13. Ioſ. 1.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; therefore haue I ſpoken, wee alſo beleeue &amp; therefore ſpeake;</hi> by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereby the Lord encouraged <hi>Ioſuah</hi> in particular againſt all enemies, euery member of Chriſt aſwell one as another, all as any one, in his iudgement, muſt be moued in all their wants to eſchew coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> and be content with ſuch things as they haue, becauſe he, that is the Lord, hath ſaid it, <hi>I wil in no caſe faile thee, neither
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15872:24"/>forſake thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 56.4, 11.13. Heb. 13:6.</note> &amp; ſeeing that kingly Prophet vpon the perſuaſion, that the <hi>Lord was his helper, did not feare what man might do vnto him,</hi> both he and other may not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Lord as their helper alſo, but vpon that hope take heart againſt the feare of all wrongs. And is it not cleare in that great queſtion, how a man ſtands righteous in the ſight of God, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.6.</note> becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> in particular was <hi>iuſtified by Faith,</hi> therefore all belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers that either haue been, are, or ſhall be iuſtified; haue beene, are, and ſhall be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith likewiſe? Aske the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> why he perſuaded euery particular perſon (to whom he ſpake) <hi>to repent and to be baptized</hi> (now euery particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert was to be baptized) <hi>in the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, for the remiſſiou of ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.38, 39.</note> and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured them they ſhould <hi>receiue the gift of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> was it not this? becauſe <hi>the promiſe was made to them &amp; to their children and to all a farre off.</hi> Plainly inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating that by how much more large the promiſe was, by ſo much more might eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in particular be bold, by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſuffering the ſeale to be fixed, to intereſt, &amp; eſtabliſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, in the couenant. <hi>Dauid</hi> in his perplexitie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15872:25"/>almoſt deſpaired of the Lords goodneſſe towards him, as appeareth in that he ſo earneſtly expoſtulateth the caſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Gods dealing with him, when he ſaith; <hi>Will the Lord abſent himſelf for euer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 77.7, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; will he be no more entreated? is his mercy cleane gone for euer, and is his promiſe come vtterly to an end for euer more? hath God for gotten to be gracious, and will he ſhut vp his louing kindneſſe in diſpleaſure?</hi> But why doth he correct his infirmitie? becauſe <hi>he forgat the yeares of the right hand of themoſt high:</hi> and how doth he recollect his ſpirits? by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the workes of the Lord,</hi> &amp; calling to mind <hi>his wonders of old time,</hi> euen thoſe (for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he mentioneth) which he had done for that whole multitude of his ancient <hi>people the Iſraelites</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deliuered them from the thraldome of Aegypt, applying to himſelf that power which was made appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent for, &amp; that Mercy, which was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to, a great number, euen a whole Nation, for his perſonall comfort.</p>
            <p>Now they themſelues make the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion:
<note place="margin">And euen of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeries themſelues.</note> For demand of one of their Prieſts why this or that particuler man or woman muſt belieue and be perſuaded his or her ſins are pardoned vpon the pronouncing of abſolution, he will ſurely, otherwiſe he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15872:25"/>cannot anſwer, Chriſt hath left that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vnto him. But demand againe where findes he that power confirmed on him? He muſt anſwere Chriſt <hi>ſaid</hi> vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Diſciples, <hi>Whoſoeuer ſins thou or yee remit, they are remitted.</hi> And now inferres he from hence, that he may remit ſinnes, &amp; that he whom he abſolues may be perſuaded of the pardon of his ſins ſeeing neither his nor the others name is there particularly expreſſed? He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but anſwere, it is becauſe he is in the place of one of the Diſciples, and what was ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles is deriued to him: doth not he now from a generall inferre a particular, or if they will from one particular, the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> intereſt another, the Pope? if this be lawfull for them and not for vs, let them produce their charter and priuiledge thus to conclude, or if it may be done in this caſe and not in any other, let them ſhew their Prouiſo, or elſe we may ſafely hold, that, <hi>What the Holy Ghost in this kinde vſeth and they practiſe, wee may lawfully vſe the ſame,</hi> and they haue no reaſon to except againſt it, namely, that from the generall promiſes and comforts of the Goſpell wee may draw particular
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15872:26"/>concluſions for the aſſuring and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our hearts in any neceſſary ſauing grace.
<note place="margin">Truth of conuerſion may bee knowne.</note> Thus is the firſt friuolous.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is as falſe: for if a Saint might not euidently perceiue his own conuerſion to be true, I would know the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why in the Scriptures we haue the notes of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance together with the proper effects of the ſame declared, if it be not this, that, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian looking in this <hi>glaſſe</hi> which yeelds the fulleſt and trueſt reſemblance of the heart might behold by due examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formitie of his ſoule to the will of God, thereby to receiue comfort &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in aſſurance of the pardon of his ſins, future happineſſe, and at all times <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparabilitie from the loue of God in Christ,</hi> and the like: for can the fire be certainly knowne by the heat,
<note place="margin">Math. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>the tree by the fruit</hi> (in our Sauiours iudgement not a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and coniecturall ſigne, but a ſure and infallible note) and ſhall not a man by the effects manifeſtly ſee his faith vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, his repentance ſound? yes ſurely: for is true repentance a ſorrow for ſins paſt, a ſtriuing with ſins preſent, a watching to preuent ſins to come, an hearty deſire, full purpoſe and conſtant indeuour to auoid euill and proſecute that which is good?
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15872:26"/>and ſhall not a man know that he is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it? Is it poſſible that a man ſhould grieue and not take notice of it, ſtriue and not feele it, watch and not perceiue it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and not diſcerne it, purpoſe and not diſcouer it, endeuour and not finde it, and doe all theſe heartily, fully and conſtantly, &amp; not euidently know it? It is not poſſible.</p>
            <p>Beſides euery regenerate man hath a a new heart, a renued ſpirit, which is a faithfull witneſſe, giuing teſtimony not to God, for that it needs not, nor to others, for that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, but to the man who hath it, for that it muſt, of the truth of thoſe things, which it knows to be in him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Gods wil, &amp; his own eternal welfare;
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.5.</note> ſeeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>a faithfull witneſſe will not lye,</hi> &amp; the ſpirit of the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtifieth the truth of his repentance may not he be as firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſuaded, as his heart faithfully wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the ſincerity of his conuerſion.</p>
            <p>But <hi>the heart of man,</hi> ſay they,
<note place="margin">Ier. 17 9. What heart it is which is deceiued.</note> 
               <hi>Is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aboue meaſure, who can know it?</hi> It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed that the vnregenerate heart (of which the Prophets ſpeach is to be conceiued) is like a filthy puddle, at the bottome wherof through the thickneſſe &amp; impurity of the water, neither one thing nor other can diſtinctly, if at all, be ſeene:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15872:27"/>but the regenerate heart, which only is the harbor of true repentance, may fitly be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a clear fountain at whoſe bottom euery thing as it is ſand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mud, baſe from better mettals, being caſt into it, may be diſcerned: &amp; howſoeuer the veſſels which are in an houſe, are not in the night ſeaſon through darkeneſſe by the eye diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; yet at the approach of either Sunne or candle, a man may take notice of, and put a difference betweene, thoſe veſſells which are appointed to honour, and theſe which are deſtinated to diſhonourable vſes: ſo that heart which is full of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall darkeneſſe admits noe exact know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of either vice or vertue, but miſtakes the one for the other in it ſelfe, yet the beames of the Sunne of tighteouſneſſe by his bleſſed Spirit entring into that heart which is become the Temple of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, nay, euen the dwelling and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place of the euer to be admired Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, enlighten euery crany and corner of it, and ſo lay vnto open view the ſinnes and ſanctities of the ſame, as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. How elſe could a Saint ſorrow for the one, or reioyce in the teſtimony of a good conſcience, be ſolaced &amp; giue praiſe vnto God, for the other?</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:15872:27"/>
            <p>And was not (ſo they doe obiect) <hi>Peter,</hi> after he was called to his Apoſtleſhip, and indued with ſauing grace, much deceiued when he boaſted: <hi>Though all men ſhould be offended, becauſe of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.33, 35.</note> 
               <hi>yet would he neuer be offended, and though he ſhould dye with him, yet he would not deny him?</hi> That <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid ſo, may not be gaineſaid, and that he was deceiued, muſt needs be granted: but that, they inferre hence more then wee affirme, may thus bee plainly manifeſted: for that wherein <hi>Peter</hi> failed, was as they ſurmiſe, his conſtant confeſſing of Chriſt; but it is only their ſurmiſe: for in euery grace, in euery dutie, there are two things to be conſidered, the grace or duty it ſelfe, and the circumſtances of it, now theſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are either ſimply and abſolutely neceſſary, or only reſpectiuely and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally requiſite to ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Be it now granted, that the grace or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherof <hi>Peter</hi> made ſo faire a ſhow, was a reſolute purpoſe, not to be offended with, but to be a confeſſour of, Chriſt his Maſter, they cannot deny, but muſt confeſſe, that thoſe circumſtances of it which were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, were, that he would not do the one, and that he would doe the other, with all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15872:28"/>willingneſſe, conſtantly, truly and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without all by-reſpect: thoſe which were ſecondary were, the continuing in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this or that moment of time, at this or that time of Chriſts proſperity or aduerſity, happy or miſerable eſtate, &amp;, as it is from his owne mouth at Chriſts death, in this or that maner or geſture, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>praying</hi> with <hi>Steuen</hi> (not ſimply pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">Act. 7.59, 61.</note> or praying feruently but praying) for himſelf <hi>ſtanding,</hi> for his perſecutours <hi>knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and will not they now confeſſe that theſe latter are things which God <hi>(who hath put the times &amp; ſeaſons in his own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp; 1.7. Rom. 14.17</note> 
               <hi>&amp; whoſe kingdome conſiſts not in outward but inward things)</hi> hath neuer promiſed; and therefore no meruaile if he failed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preuailing and preſuming are ſeldome or neuer met walking in the ſame path, or poſſeſſed by the ſame perſon at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>But now his willingneſſe, truth, ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; the like (conditions, without which a grace is no grace, a duty no duty promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to, and through the preſence of Gods gracious Spirit alwaies in ſome meaſure reſident, in, the Saints) in that his reſolute promiſe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> were, as the fruits of a good <hi>tree,</hi> though not at altimes without intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15872:28"/>and ſo not at that time, to be ſeen han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging on the boughs; yet alwaies in the root in that <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> which God had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined as moſt due and conuenient, ready to be made apparent.</p>
            <p>As therefore we will not affirm that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was neuer offended becauſe of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Wherein <hi>Peter</hi> in that Proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</note> ſo they in their conſciences muſt needes grant that, as <hi>Dauid</hi> hath taught vs to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh, he was not offended with him <hi>for euer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.25.</note> and though he died not with him as he pretended, yet he died ſeazed of the grace of confeſſing him as his heart then perſuaded, nay, he died for him as he then purpoſed, and as the euent it ſelfe after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that I may turne the point of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi> owne weapon againſt himſelfe, who had receiued ſure by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God, ſeeing him argue againſt the light of his owne conſcience, ſome great ſtroake on his head, which did much confound his memory and beſot his iudgement when he thought vpon the deceitfuleeſſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> (rather <hi>Sauls</hi>) heart <hi>raging againſt the Church,</hi> ſeeing he was then an vnbelieuer,
<note place="margin">Abſurd to alledge <hi>Pauls</hi> rage againſt the Church to proue a St. may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</note> and could not poſſibly then be acquainted with that certainty of faith which is the elects peculiar: and howſoeuer as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth truly (hauing a little as it ſeemeth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15872:29"/>recouered his ſenſes) ſo far as ignorance, and inclination or affection to ſinne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth, ſo farre is doubting powerfull, yet he proclaimeth his, either ignorance, blindneſſe, or wilfull delight in error, in in that he laboureth wholly to depriue the ſonnes of God of that meaſure of aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance concerning their eternal priuiledges which is anſwerable to that degree of ſauing faith,
<note place="margin">According to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of faith is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Saints aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance. 1 Cor. 13.3.</note> wherewith, be it leſſe or more, they are vndenyably enriched: and though ſome may <hi>giue almes</hi> out of vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory to be ſeene of men, and other ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their <hi>bodies to bee burned</hi> for hereſie wanting, in doing both and either, true <hi>Charity,</hi> thinking notwithſtanding they doe men and God good ſeruice, yet this doing is ſo farre from any meaſure of, that it hath no affinitie with, true conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which cauſeth a man if he fayleth in the one, not to let God reſt till it be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; in feare of the other, to pierce the cloudes with feruent cryes that, it may be preuented, whoſe humble breathings iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſuch a breaſt, draw in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of Gods Spirit, &amp; are refreſhed with a peruſaſion grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods promiſes, that, in Chriſt, his ſuit ſhal either be gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted or his deſire for the deed freely accepted.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:15872:29"/>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay then to thoſe who would haue all the S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> to remain in a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering doubt, &amp; that of duty, concerning their eternall ſafety? Deale they not like watermen in their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; are they not enemies, dangerous enemies, to mens ſouls in the maintaining of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?
<note place="margin">Of all, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts haue leaſt reaſon to doubt of ſaluation.</note> Watermen they are, for while they labour for <hi>Gueſſe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture,</hi> taking in their hands the two oares of the Law &amp; the Goſpel, do they not look another, euen the quite contrary way? for how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they want the help of the Law for their certaine aſſurance of life eternall, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they teach, &amp; would haue no man to doubt that they may yeeld to it full obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yea, and performe more then it lyeth vpon them towards the ſupplying of the wants of other? and how is it poſſible that they ſhould be deſtitute of the Goſpels furtherance for the ſetling of their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence when as they of all the men in the world, &amp; none but they, if we ſhall belieue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, are the true belieuers? Me thinks they being perſuaded reſolutely of either of theſe ſeuerally, ſhould not be in ſuſpition to be damned, but being aſſured of both theſe ioyntly together, how is it poſſible, that they ſhold only be in a coiecture to be ſaued? vnles it be iuſt with God, to mingle
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15872:30"/>their meanes of aſſurance with doubting to attaine the aime and end of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience &amp; pluck downe the plumes of their faith with a feare of failing in their hopes, ſeeing they ioyn with Chriſts al-ſufficient, their own al-deficient merits, and will be iuſtified by their works, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God wil not.</p>
            <p>But to leaue them to their ſtrong deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">To hold doubting neceſſary is dangerous.</note> how dangerous are they to the ſoules of men, while they preſſe vpon the people this continuing in doubt of future ioyes, &amp; of preſent good eſtate, as neceſſary? Do they not paue before them the path which will without any hinderance leade them ſo,
<note place="margin">Such a doubting as admits no aſſurance makes prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er fruitleſſe.</note> as they ſhall vndoubtedly miſſe of what God hath promiſed? for hath God in his reuealed will made knowne his good and vnalterable purpoſe for conferring vpon his choſen the glory of the life to come? and muſt his children expect, and in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation pray for, the accompliſhing of their hope and his promiſe? muſt prayer be powred out with feruency? and can there be feruency where there is an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine faith? or if their faith be doubting, can their prayer preuaile? Surely Saint <hi>Iames</hi> thought verily, whatſoeuer theſe Romiſh Sophiſters imagine, that asking and beleeuing, nay ſuch a belieuing, as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15872:30"/>ought to be ſeuered from euery doubting, are to be inſeparably ioyned together,
<note place="margin">Iames 1.6.</note> when he bids euery Saint <hi>Aske in faith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubting,</hi> and taketh it for vndenya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, howſoeuer they conceit it, that the more doubting there is in asking, the leſſe hope there is of ſpeeding, nay, if there be nothing but doubting, there cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expectation of enioying when he poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely affirmeth that,
<note place="margin">verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>That man muſt not ſo much as thinkee that he ſhall receiue any thing of the Lord.</hi> To haue then a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt, be the aſſault what it will be, to continue neceſſarily in onely a coniect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urall and vncertaine gueſſe, that <hi>He ſhall be well,</hi> is it not to draw on the ſoule from vncertain doubting to certain deſpairing? and to moue the Lord not only to a deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his prayer, but euen a diſtaſte of both prayer and perſon? for is it not a calling of Gods promiſes into queſtion, as if they were either only pretended or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, as if man by no meanes could be capable of them? Is not the truth of God hereby impeached, peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnſetled, hope diſheartened, patience deceiued, our loue to God diminiſhed, &amp; the beſt man diſcouraged in the courſe of grace? what difference betwixt <hi>him that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15872:31"/>liueth by,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26.13. &amp; 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>and him that hath no hope in the time of tryall?</hi> Shall not both pretend <hi>a Lyon in the way (which to both is an hedge of thornes) and either ſhun the combate or be diſcomfited in the conflict?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 14.5. Pro. 28.1.</note> Shall they <hi>not feare where no feare is, and fly when none purſueth,</hi> and beholding the fury of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Iudge,
<note place="margin">Reu. 6.16.</note> wiſh in deſpaire <hi>the Mountains might fall vpon them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, bleſſed be God, euery one of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is ſo far from hauing cauſe to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in his trials that he hath, through an holy confidenc,
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.32.</note> 
               <hi>hope euen in his death;</hi> for it is the nature of true faith to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<note place="margin">Gen. 32.26.</note> and to wreſtle as <hi>Iacob</hi> euen <hi>with God himſelfe,</hi> and not to ceaſe till it be partaker of <hi>the bleſſing.</hi> It brings the promiſes of God and preſents them to the eye of the minde, not ſuffering them to depart till it from them hath ſucked ſome comfortable ſolace.
<note place="margin">No preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> Let not vs then contemne that as preſumptuous which the Lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, yea, commanded as precious: for that which he hath appointed to be found, is ingratitude in vs not to ſeeke that which he hath aduiſed vs to haue is negligence in vs to want, &amp; that which he hath enioyned vs to haue in high regard, is diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to neglect ſeeing we may ſafely ſaile between
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15872:31"/>the gulfe of preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dammage flye between the ſcorching Sunne of ſecurity &amp; the cooling ſea of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire; ſo as neither the wings of our ſouls in our paſſage to heauen ſhall melt by the one, not becom ſtiffe by the other: for kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping within the compaſſe of our holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, we ſhall continue ſafely in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian motion till we reſt vpon the battle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Celeſtiall manſion.</p>
            <p>How is it then that we ſeeke ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety in earthly things? In them we wil do nothing without mature aduiſe &amp; great conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for to inueſt vs furely in our temporall inheritance, the Euidence muſt be carefully drawne, what is ſuperfluous razed out, what is wanting ſupplyed, &amp; if any thing may only be ſuſpected to ouer throw our tenure, the couenant is renued, other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions are concluded, &amp; if about theſe any doubt ariſe a new courſe is deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Thus we make that ſure we are ſure to looſe, carefull to haue things tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, clods of clay for our bodies which are houſes of earth. And ſhall we not aſpire vnto certainty in our ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall endowments without which we faint in miſeries, faile of Gods mercies, &amp; haue no intereſt in Chriſts merits? Shall we not endeuour reſolution in and againſt our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15872:32"/>doubtings concerning our heauenly inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, through which the ſoule in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings is comforted, the conſcience in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations is quieted, and the whole man in all oppoſitions is ſecured.</p>
            <p>Aſſurance is a gift of the Spirit,
<note place="margin">Meanes to obraine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance.</note> now the Spirit it ſelfe is giuen to thoſe that in faith &amp; feruency aske it: the word is the Lords mouth which promiſeth it and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are his hands which ſeale it to vs, Motions to aſſurace are raiſed in the heart by the Spirit, and theſe muſt not be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. Nouriſh the hatred, extinguiſh the delight, of euery ſin, and daily encreaſe &amp; continue our deſires and endeuours for the reforming of euery euill, if the flax of affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance onely ſmoake, we muſt blow it with ſerious meditating vpon Gods Couenant, and an-humble applying of his promiſes, inflame it with obſeruing the truth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards others, but eſpecially by finding experience of the ſpirits power in our ſelues, and cauſe it to burne with the true acquaintnance of that bleſſed, holy, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer happy vnion which is betwixt God and vs, and by being abundant in good workes: for that hath a ſecret bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Now this fire will be known if we find in other,
<note place="margin">Signes of ſſurance.</note> &amp; perceiue in our ſelues the fruits
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15872:32"/>of the Spirit, if we be continually armed in euery part, if we be confident in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects that are good, &amp; reſt contented in oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences that are croſſe, &amp; depend vpon the Lord for things euen of this life (a duty which Chriſt inſinuated when he taught vs to pray for <hi>our daily bread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>before our ſins forgiueneſſe</hi>) if we can ſcorne &amp; hold all things in this life, nay life it ſelf, contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible in compariſon of Chriſt &amp; his croſſe, beare the brunt of the greateſt oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s patiently &amp; couragiouſly for his truth, &amp; that to the end, ſtand vpon God only his power &amp; prouidence in all our tryals: if it ſuppreſſe all naturall feares, ſubdue all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolicall aſſaults, proceed from an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Gods promiſes after repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; if that apprehenſion be ſeconded with the ſecret teſtimony of Gods ſpirit, rhere is no doubt of this ſound aſſurance which is common to all the Saints.</p>
            <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all the Saints?
<note place="margin">Outward conditions ſhould not exalt a Sr. too much aboue his inferiour brother.</note> why ſhould then any outward condition cauſe any to exalt himſelfe aboue his bretheren, or to ſwell againſt thoſe that are endued with the ſame at leaſt ſome if not greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſpirituall graces? ſhould not <hi>euen this</hi> moue them <hi>to make</hi> themſelues <hi>equall with thoſe of the lower ſort:</hi> and may not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15872:33"/>euen the meaneſt among Chriſts members ſolace themſelues in this that they are not excluded from aſſurance of their intereſt in life eternall,
<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Saint to be ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced hereby.</note> but may, in ſome meaſure, many times in a greater meaſure, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other of eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children of God, that in the eies of the world are more eſteemed, be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of their ſtate? ſhould not the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this moderate all their mourning &amp; become a medicine for al their maladies which ariſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worldly wants or wrongs? Be they neuer ſo much diſtreſſed or deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they may ſecurely repoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in their holy confidence,
<note place="margin">How to be comforted by aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in ſint and ſufferings.</note> for being renued in their minds &amp; bodies the deadly arrowes of ſin and ſufferings are dipt in the blood of Chriſt, who like a good Phiſitian will take care to heale their wounds with his own hands, &amp; either take away from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maladies as from <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 37. &amp; 38.</note> or free them from the miſchiefe of them, by miniſtring an Antidote to their poyſon,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1, 4, 5 &amp; 12.9. Luke 16.</note> as in <hi>Paul;</hi> or in his appointed time, by remouing them, as he did <hi>Lazarus</hi> to glory. To which the Lord in <hi>his</hi> mercy bring vs for his Chriſts merits, To whom with the bleſſed ſpirit, One <hi>God in Eſſence, three in Perſons,</hi> be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed all honour, praiſe, and power, now and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15872:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
